if you're making vertical reels for
tick-tock instagram reels or youtube
shorts there's no reason it can't be
just as precisely edited as a netflix
show and today i'm going to show you how
to get started doing that in final cut
pro also this video is brought to you by
art list more about them later for the
sake of this video let's assume that
we're shooting on our iphones and i'm
going to edit this reel that i just did
for my wife last night actually her
nails getting done very simple and i'm
just going to select them all and
airdrop them to myself the first couple
steps are in the finder before we move
into final cut i'm going to select all
of those downloaded videos create a new
folder and call it i don't know whatever
the project's going to be so
anya's nails
then inside that anya's nails i'm going
to create a new folder and call it media
and this media folder might have videos
or images in this case just videos but
it could have anything in there so i'm
going to head over to final cut pro and
create a new library and then i can save
it inside that anya's nails folder
and all this is moving too fast at the
end of the video i'll have links to all
my final cut videos that'll go even more
in depth on some of these steps because
i know i can move a little quickly
something to point out along the way i
do create a library for each project
that i'm working on so here was one from
kew gardens another from las vegas
now inside this library we're going to
create a new project now we're going to
have to click use custom settings here
because we're not doing things totally
standard this isn't a horizontal video
it's a vertical video
this is basically the whole key step
here final cut recently introduced these
vertical templates that weren't there
before and something important to note
is it often defaults to 720 by 1280 i
don't know why like not even 1080 you
want it to at least be 1080 by 1920
that's proper hd
and 29.97 is the most common frame rate
um if you're shooting on a phone so i'm
gonna stick with that you're gonna have
to look at your footage to check what
you actually did but if you don't know
what frame rate you shot at it's
probably
okay things are taking a little more
shape let's go to the next step and
we'll go to file
import media
in the media folder we've got all of the
videos and i'm just going to shift-click
to select all of them because you're
going to import everything at once and i
want to draw attention to this option on
the right here it says copy to library
or leave files in place if you've
watched my other final cut videos i like
to leave files in place for more
advanced edits but since we're doing a
simple one here i'm going to say copy to
library this is the default what final
cut typically does so we're going to use
that not worry about any of these other
options here and just say import
selected and now let's go back to finder
take another look at what happened here
so there's no confusion here's all that
original media this is where those
videos are that we started with now if
we click on the library you'll see the
size of it has grown it's 440 megabytes
now that's because it copied all of
these inside of this library so i can
actually delete that folder if i go back
in my project i can confirm all the
videos are still there because there's a
copy that final cut made and it's in
that library all these different
interface areas can be resized so that
we can do a little bit of custom scaling
i'd really like to see final cut let me
make this as big as i want like put the
vertical video on the right of the
screen you can't do that right now all
you can really do is stretch it up and
down because you want to see as much of
it as possible so all i have to do is
select all of them and i'm just going to
drag them down here into the timeline
and to make this the easiest edit in
history now that all this is in here i
know that it just needs to kind of run
sequentially all i'm going to do is say
command a so i select all i'm going to
right click
and say change duration to one second
and just like that my timeline's gone
down from seven minutes to uh 23 seconds
and if you're editing for social media
that's probably more realistic now
before i hit play i know that the audio
in this is not useful so i'm going to
select all these clips i can click and
drag and over here in the inspector
you'll see a little audio icon if you
hover over it'll tell you what they do
this is the audio inspector i'm going to
click on it
and turn the volume all the way down so
none of these clips have volume anymore
you see that at the bottom that there
was a little waveform if i turn them
back up if i turn them down that
waveform is gone so there's no audio
and now i can just play so if you've got
a montage just clips that go one after
the other this is a really quick way to
get them in order but sometimes you need
to select a certain part of it so for
example these two last clips they're not
really showing what she intended so i'm
going to click on the clip drag it out
and now i can see the whole thing you
see how i did that either side has
little handles that turn yellow
and red as you click on them and then
you know that you're grabbing onto the
edges of the clip red means you can't
drag it any further in that direction
yellow means it's got some room to move
and if you're seeing something different
right now i'm on the default select tool
the shortcut for that is a and other
tools will behave differently but this
is the one that we use most often so you
can hit a to make sure you're using the
same default tool that i am and expand
this out and so what i'm looking for is
where anya shows off her nails here just
like that now i can just click on the
right drag that shorter find where the
clip begins
drag that over here and i've got two
different takes of this but i don't need
the second one now i chose this take
and now i've got a full sequence like
this could be the reel just like this
but of course we're going to take a
little bit further let's say i want to
change which part of the clip i'm
viewing i press command plus to zoom in
obviously command minus would zoom out
and in our tools instead of the default
select i'm going to use trim and what
this does is as i click in the middle of
the clip it's moving which part of the
clip is being used so i can just kind of
move it around until it's using the part
that i want these are incredibly short
here's a better example so in this one
you can't even see the nail being
painted so i'm going to move it over
until we do now let's watch it
great half a second of a nail being
painted now let's say you don't want to
use one of these clips great chance to
show off the magnetic timeline that
you've heard so much about this is what
a lot of people love about final cut i
can just click on a clip press delete
and they snap together like magnets i'm
going to undo redo so you see what's
happening there it's kind of got gravity
towards the left so that it always wants
to close any spaces that you create in
the timeline so if i move back to the
start and i hit play which is also
spacebar i can see well great i've got a
reel of some nails being done
cool
now i know you might be really invested
in this nail video we made but let's
move to an even more exciting one this
one we just did in las vegas it's a lot
more exciting to watch but it's still
missing something important that's music
and i know just where to find it and go
straight to artless dot io where i've
been getting stock music for years now
because it's not just music they have
lots of sound effects too so let me show
you just how quick and easy it is to
find a song i can say video theme i
already know that this is a travel video
and now it gives me a pre-selected list
of great travel songs i can narrow it
down by things like the amount of energy
that i want it to have let's say it's
medium fast and then i can also add a
genre let's say this is gonna be a pop
song once i find something that i like
the vibe of it i can also click this
button over here and it's gonna
recommend more similar songs that have
the same tone or the same speed once i
found one i like i can just click
download mp3 to keep it small
i'm going to put it in my media folder
and i can actually just drag it into
final cut it's another way to add things
i'm going to put it below
all of the video and i'll show you how
easy it is to edit the video to the beat
but first a few more things about art
list they've got some great licensing
options to get you access to unlimited
music and sound effects starting with
the personal plan at 9.99 or if you need
to cover more uses like broadcast tv
paid ads or any online platform you can
get the unlimited plan for 1660 a month
which really gives you this confidence
when you're doing commercial videos that
your client is going to get exactly what
they're expecting and now is a great
time to sign up because they've got this
all in pack that just provides a ton of
different features like sound effects
visual effects in fact i'm going to drop
in one of their included film mats that
is in the bundle you can also add their
film grain and also these color preset
luts and all of a sudden my video looks
a lot more like film so you've got a
worldwide license at a great price and
our list is always adding more songs and
more musicians so you can stay ahead of
the trends so sign up now because it
lets them know you heard about art list
on this channel and it also gets you
that all impact with the presets and the
sound effects and the vfx and then you
will also get two months free at art
list again link is in the description
thanks again to our list so now if i hit
play you get all of it okay but i want
to time this a little better so i'm
going to cut some of the beginning of
this video off and bring this way
forward so that the drop happens right
as that first shot ends another thing
you can see happening is that it's
snapping between the clips that's this
thing over here see snap it'll snap from
clip to clip and i can drag this over
and now we should get a nice perfectly
timed drop
[Music]
perfect when you want to end the song
you can click on any segment and press
command
b and now it is cut those in half it's a
blade b is for blade here is the blade
tool as well now using my default select
tool i'm going to select the end of that
and delete it and now the song
is the length of the video i'm just
going to drag out that end and it will
snap to the very last moment now that
we've got music in here i'm just going
to show you how easy it is to edit to
the beat without even listening to the
song i know that these yellow peaks are
when the beat is hitting so i can just
click and drag each clip to line up with
that
if i play it all back i've got 17 epic
seconds of our recent trip to las vegas
[Music]
all right now the last step we're going
to export this all we got to do is go to
file share
export you want to double check down
here that the settings are what you
expected 1080 by 1920 and 29.97 frames
per second also up here the only thing
you want to change is go over to
settings and this is where you set the
format i don't know what it defaults to
but let's choose a useful one i often
use apple devices and go to better
encoding h264
and make sure that the resolution is
turned up as high as it can be that's
all you got to do
hit next and i'm just going to save it
into this folder with all my other reels
if you want to watch progress you can
click this little circle up here and see
it export we covered the simplest way to
edit it but i know i can talk a little
fast so i'm going to go through it all
again and throw in a few more pro tips
this time with a real of my photography
and videos that we shot on another
recent trip it was all shot on film
actually this is the yashica t4 super d
the first steps are similar i'm going to
go on my phone and find all of the
images i want to use air drop them to my
computer create a new folder called euro
trip film
inside i'll make a media folder this
time i'll have photos videos
and audio and you'll see why i'm making
manual folders in two seconds because
i'm going to organize it myself this
time i'll select and drag
all the video and all the photos
i'll go back to our list use some of the
playlists i've already created and just
download a song and add it to the audio
folder now i'm all organized in the
finder time to get back to final cut
i'm going to create file new library put
it in eurotrip film and give it whatever
name you want now i'm going to import
things a little bit differently first
i'm going to change the default
preference of this by going to
preferences and i want to leave files in
place this is how i do things for
youtube and any more important serious
editing project and then i'm going to go
to file
import media again if i open up your
trip film here's all the photos and
videos that i plan to use now i'm going
to press command a to select all those
files and look over here to the right
we're going to use leave files in place
i already organized them i know where
they are i don't need to copy them to my
library and i'm going to say import all
again ignoring everything over here on
the right and i don't have a project yet
so i'm going to create a new project
again i'll use that vertical template
this time i'm going to make it 4k which
is 2160 by 3840 same frame rate i'm
going to quickly name it here again this
is the one that actually changes the
export name of your final file the
project name so this one kind of matters
a little more i guess and click ok so
i've got a timeline at the bottom over
here on my left in the browser i have
all of my photos and videos and i still
want this to be really quick but i want
to be a little more precise about what i
add in so i'm going to zoom in and see
what these clips look like instead of
just dragging them all in i'm going to
select my favorite section from each
clip it's going to kind of play out like
a vlog so i'll start with this video of
traveling from calgary to london and a
concept that's in all video editing
software so this is transferable you can
press i and that's going to select an in
point see how the selection moved this
little yellow selector at the end of the
part i want to use i'm going to press o
and that's in and out now you see this
is what is selected in the clip i can
click and drag this down to the timeline
i also have some buttons here that will
help move it down to the timeline if i
want but for now let's just click and
drag to keep it simple
and you can see i'm really quickly just
skimming over these videos selecting my
favorite parts and dragging them down
i'm trying not to be too picky about it
i can refine it later but also the point
of reels or tic tocs are to post a lot
of them so just think quickly follow
your instincts just choose the best part
of the clip as soon as you see it
again i'm not going to use any of this
audio so i will command a to select all
i'm going to turn the volume all the way
down and then go into my audio keyword
and here is that art list song and i can
just drag it down below command minus to
zoom out of my timeline grab the end of
it make it the same length as the clips
since i know i've selected the best
parts and i know i want this video to
move fast i can select all again and say
right click change duration and i can
make this
15 frames now each one's only gonna be
half a second because i know i want this
one to move quickly also notice that i
put two clips in the wrong place this is
loading filament to the camera that
should be near the beginning so i can
just click and drag and the magnetic
timeline will help me out and the other
thing i want in this reel is to show the
results from these video clips so now i
just kind of need to match them all up
photos to the videos that they align
with
so first i know i want those cactuses
there they are i'm just going to drag it
down
drop it in right after the digital
cactus and there it is there's the
result grab the side make it shorter and
now you notice there's black bars on the
top and bottom maybe i want those maybe
i don't i'm going to say that i don't
and over here in the inspector if you
scroll to the bottom there's spatial
conform right now it's set to fit i'm
going to switch that to fill it's going
to make the image the same size as the
frame so now i've got no more black bars
after i've finished adding all the clips
in i'm going to select them all again
and let's do that right click make
everything half a second again including
the photos and also whether selected i'm
going to click this little film icon
over here in the inspector scroll down
to the bottom
spatial conform we're going to fill so
they all are full frame and after i
adjust the timing a little bit more this
is my video
[Music]
now if you're confused about editing the
instagram reels tick tock or any other
vertical video you're working on don't
worry i've got more final cut pro
tutorials that go even more in depth so
click on that video watch it next and
i'll see you in the next
[Music]
you